<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-09T03:45:22+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Siddhant Midha</title><subtitle>personal site </subtitle><entry><title type="html">mipt</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/mipt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="mipt"/><published>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/mipt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/mipt/"><![CDATA[<p>compilation of results in the MIPT arena.</p> <h2 id="random-quantum-circuits">Random quantum circuits</h2> <ol> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1808.06134.pdf">Quantum Zeno Effect and the Many-body Entanglement Transition</a>: This paper is one of those starting the discussion on MIPT explicitly: they provide numerics for entanglement entropy dynamics in large-scale Clifford and small Haar-random models sprinkled with measurements. Notably, they perform a scaling analysis of the steady-state EE as well as the dynamics.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1901.08092.pdf">Measurement-driven entanglement transition in hybrid quantum circuits</a>: This paper continues the discussion initiated previously with extensive numerics on multiple models. What I like most here is the distribution of the stabilizer lengths as the measurement strength is varied – the entanglement phase transition is <em>clearly</em> elucidated because of continuous vanishing of the peak in the distribution at ‘large’ lengths. Moreover, the logarithmic correction in the volume law is clearly outlined, and can be explained by this length distribution! Lastly, they carry over the RQC analysis to systematic models – which lack randomness in (i) measurement locations and/or (ii) unitaries, attempting to make the point that such hybrid circuits will generically show a volume-law to area-law transition. Also, initial state independence. Wink, wink.</li> </ol> <h2 id="fermionic-systems">Fermionic Systems</h2> <ol> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.04638">Entanglement in a free fermion chain under continuous monitoring</a>: This paper studies the entanglement dynamics in a free fermion chain under continuous measurement of all occupation numbers with a quasiparticle pair approach. They point out that the volume law is unstable to <em>any</em> $p &gt; 0$ measurement strength, because of finite coherent lifetime under measurement.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.10837.pdf">Growth of entanglement entropy under local projective measurements</a>: If $1/\tau$ is the measurement rate, then these guys show that for a fermionic chain with PBC and monitoring of local number operator, then the critical time $\tau_c$ for the switchover from area to volume law diverges with the length, hence the thermodynamic limit would only exhibit an area-law of the saturated EE!</li> </ol> <h2 id="emergent-quantum-codes">Emergent quantum codes</h2> <ol> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1903.05124">Quantum Error Correction in Scrambling Dynamics and Measurement-Induced Phase Transition</a></li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.05195">Dynamical purification phase transitions induced by quantum measurements</a>: This paper formalizes the emergent quantum error correcting code formed by monitored circuits, and lays out the theory for such codes by quantifying the channel capacity in the thermodynamic limit.</li> </ol> <h2 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h2> <ol> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2306.17161.pdf">Optimized trajectory unraveling for classical simulation of noisy quantum dynamics</a>: The MIPT setting is now used in the viewpoint of <em>simulability</em> of the monitored system. The idea is that the volume-law phase is classically difficult to simulate while the area-law is not, so if one can <em>decrease</em> the critical measurement strength required to enter area-law, one makes the quantum system simulable for a larger parameter setting. This paper thus discusses optimized unravellings to perform this task, in both RQCs (by mapping to stat-mech models) and an Ising chain far from integrability.</li> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2301.05195.pdf">A numerical study of measurement-induced phase transitions in the Sachdev-Ye-Kitaev model</a>: The authors study the MIPT in the all-to-all coupled SYK model by Jordan-Wigner’ing to spins and performing exact diagonalization. Their measurement model consists of first a coin flip to decide whether or not a measurement happens (w/ rate $\Gamma$), then sampling from a Binomial distribution (parameter $p$) to decide which spins to measure. This gives a 2D phase diagram, and it is pointed out that even at $p = 1$ there is a non-zero measurement rate for the entanglement MIPT, whereas the purification MIPT is trivial, marking a concrete distinction.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[papers]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ph.D. applications</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/grad-school/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ph.D. applications"/><published>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/grad-school</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/grad-school/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2> <p>All of the content below is a result of my experience with grad school applications, and is by no means a complete or correct set of rules one needs to follow. These are just guidelines which hopefully will be helpful in crafting your own Ph.D. journey. And with that said, while most of what I say is catered to <em>Ph.D. applications in the U.S.A.</em>, some things might be generalized to M.S. applications, and Ph.D. applications elsewhere.</p> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>As a reader of this page, you might be in one of many stages possible vis-à-vis grad applications, but all of those stages reasonably converge into making sure you get into one of the suitable grad schools to do your research. You could be a first- or second-year undergrad starting to get into research, or a final year undergrad close to the applications deadline. Keeping this in mind, I’ll take a bottom-up approach and try my best to start from the beginning.</p> <h2 id="first-year-of-your-undergrad">First-year of your undergrad</h2> <p>Depending on how one likes to do and plan things, this might be too early to actually start doing anything research wise, but I’ll still talk about some things that might be helpful.</p>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a mini-guide]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">qec papers</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/qec/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="qec papers"/><published>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/qec</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2024/qec/"><![CDATA[<p>Important papers in quantum error correction.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/quant-ph/9604022">Quantum data processing and error correction</a>: <em>Perfect error correction is possible iff the coherent information equals initial entropy, i.e.,</em> $I(R:E’) = 0$. Terms like coherent information, entropy exchange, and entanglement fidelity are defined, and a data processing inequality on the coherent information is stated.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[papers]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>