<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-02T00:50:02+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Siddhant Midha</title><subtitle>personal site </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Some Fermionic Stuff</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some Fermionic Stuff"/><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="fermions">Fermions</h2> <p>In the language of second quantization, we describe fermions in terms of the annhilation \(c\) and creation operators \(c^\dagger\). Consider a system of \(N\) fermionic modes. Then, the anti-commutation relations are as follows:</p> \[\{ c_i,c_j^\dagger \} = \delta_{ij} , \{ c_i^\dagger,c_j^\dagger \} = 0, \{ c_i,c_j \} = 0\] <p>The corresponding Majorana operators are defined as,</p> \[\gamma_i := (a_i + a_i^\dagger) , \bar{\gamma}_i := -\iota (a_i - a_i^\dagger)\] <p>These objects are Hermitian, \(\gamma = \gamma^\dagger\) and \(\bar{\gamma} = \bar{\gamma}^\dagger\), and they satisfy the following anti-commutation relations,</p> \[\{ \gamma_i,\gamma_j \} = 2\delta_{ij}\] <p>Another interesting object to define in terms of the Majorana operators are <em>edge</em> and <em>vertex</em> operators. For each \(i,j \in [N]\),</p> \[E_{ij} := -\iota \gamma_i\gamma_j, V_j:= -\iota \gamma_j \bar{\gamma}_j\] <p>These objects are Hermitian, traceless, and self-inverse. They obey a nice graph-theoretic notion of (anti-)commutativity. That is, if a vertex is shared among these objects, they anticommute. If they are disjoint, they commute.</p> \[\{ E_{jk},V_j \} = 0, \{ E_{ij},E_{jk} \} = 0\] <p>and if \((i,j,k,l)\) are all distinct, then</p> \[[V_i,V_j] = 0, [E_{ij},V_k] = 0, [E_{ij},E_{kl}] = 0.\] <h2 id="parity-superselection-rule">Parity (superselection rule)</h2> <p>The number operator for mode \(i\) is defined as \(n_i = c_i^\dagger c_i\), and the total number operator is \(n = \sum_i n_i\). With this, we define the parity operator as follows,</p> \[\mathcal{P} := (-1)^n.\] <p>The parity superselection rule tells us the following: nature does not allow physical states to be in coherent superposition of states with different parity. Phrased another way, every physical state has to be in a definite parity sector. Furthermore, <em>physical</em> operations then must respect parity: they must commute with the parity operator. That is why one never sees a term like \(c + c^\dagger\) in a fermionic Hamiltonian, or why one can never measure such an operator. To obtain insight into this “rule,” let us consider the following <em>gedankenexperimente</em>. Consider two parties, Alice and Bob. They share the following (non-normalized) state</p> \[|\psi\rangle = (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>where $$</td> <td>\Omega\rangle \(is the vacuum. We see that this state is a superposition of different parities. Now suppose Alice wants to send one bit of classical information to Bob, with\)b \in { 0,1 }$$. Define</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[U_0 := I ,U_1 := \iota(c_A^\dagger - c_A)\] <p>Corresponding to the value of the bit \(b\), Alice applies the unitary \(U_b\), and Bob measures the operator \(\mathcal{O}=(1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger)\). Then, we claim that this allows deterministic superluminal communication of the bit \(b\). Note that this is not a teleportation like claim, where we actually have to send some information to tell Bob the correct basis to measure in. The <em>weird</em> thing about this is that, the basis is determined already. We now see that this is true just because of the anticommutation relations, thereby showing (empirically, atleast) parity superselection. The result after applying the unitary is,</p> \[|\psi_0\rangle = (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle\] \[|\psi_1\rangle = (1-c_B^\dagger)c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle\] \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_0\rangle= (1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger) (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle =2(|\Omega\rangle + c_B^\dagger|\Omega\rangle) = 2|\psi_0\rangle\] \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_1\rangle = (1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger)(1-c_B^\dagger)c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle = c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle - c_B^\dagger c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle - c_A^\dagger|\Omega\rangle + c_B^\dagger c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle = 0\] <p>Thus, both of these states are eigenstates of the operator \(\mathcal{O}\), viz.</p> \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_b\rangle = E_b|\psi_b\rangle\] <p>and measuring this observable thus perfectly distinguishes them, and Alice manages to transmit the bit perfectly at superluminal speed. We reach a contradiction.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol> <li>Derby, Charles, et al. “Compact fermion to qubit mappings.” Physical Review B 104.3 (2021): 035118.</li> <li>Szalay, Szilárd, et al. “Fermionic systems for quantum information people.” Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 54.39 (2021): 393001.</li> <li>Vidal, Nicetu Tibau, et al. “Quantum operations in an information theory for fermions.” Physical Review A 104.3 (2021): 032411.</li> <li>Friis, Nicolai, Antony R. Lee, and David Edward Bruschi. “Fermionic-mode entanglement in quantum information.” Physical Review A—Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics 87.2 (2013): 022338.</li> <li>Grace Sommers (QEC Journal Club, Princeton)</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="distill"/><category term="formatting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fermions In the language of second quantization, we describe fermions in terms of the annhilation \(c\) and creation operators \(c^\dagger\). Consider a system of \(N\) fermionic modes. Then, the anti-commutation relations are as follows:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>