<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-10T17:28:38+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Siddhant Midha</title><subtitle>personal site </subtitle><entry><title type="html">briefs on algebras</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/algebras/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="briefs on algebras"/><published>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/algebras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/algebras/"><![CDATA[<p>An algebra is a vector space with more to do with. Formally, if \(V\) is a vector space over the field \(\mathbb{F}\), then an algebra \(\mathcal{A}\) over \(\mathbb{F}\) is the vector space together with a bilinear multiplication operation defined on it, \(\mathcal{A} = (F,\cdot)\) with \(\cdot: V\times V \to V\), \((a,b) \mapsto a\cdot b \equiv ab\) for \(a,b\in V\). The multiplication is usually associative, \(a(bc) = (ab)c\), hence usally the algebras are associative algebras.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>A norm $$</td> <td> </td> <td>\cdot</td> <td> </td> <td>\(on\)\mathcal{A}\(is said to be _submultiplicative_ if\)</td> <td> </td> <td>ab</td> <td> </td> <td>\leq</td> <td> </td> <td>a</td> <td> </td> <td>\cdot</td> <td> </td> <td>b</td> <td> </td> <td>\(. If so, the pair\)(\mathcal{A},</td> <td> </td> <td>\cdot</td> <td> </td> <td>)$$ is a <em>normed</em> algebra.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>If further \(\mathcal{A}\) admits a unit element, satisfying \(a1 = 1a = a\) and $$</td> <td> </td> <td>1</td> <td> </td> <td>= 1\(we say that\)\mathcal{A}$$ is a <em>unital</em> normed algebra.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>As a reminder, a normed vector space in which every Cauchy sequence converges (w.r.t. that norm) is called complete. A complete normed vector space is a Banach space (if the norm is induced by an inner product, we have a Hilbert space.) Naturally, a complete normed algebra is called a Banach algebra.</p> <p>For a unital algebra, say that an element \(a\in\mathcal{A}\) is invertible if there exists a \(b\in\mathcal{A}\) such that \(ab = ba = 1\). The set of invertible elements \(\text{Inv}(\mathcal{A})\) of a unital algebra is a group under multiplication. Now, we can define the <em>spectrum</em> of an element \(a\in\mathcal{A}\) in a unital algebra as follows (note that we don’t need the element to “act” on anything)</p> <p>\begin{equation} \sigma(a) := {\lambda \in \mathbb{C} \mid \lambda 1 - a \not\in\text{Inv}(\mathcal{A})} \end{equation}</p> <p>Now, we can impose some more structure, because why not. An <em>involution</em> \(*\) on an algebra is a conjugate-linear map \(a\mapsto a^*\) such that \(a^{**} = a\) and \((ab)^* = b^* a^*\). The pair \((\mathcal{A},*)\) is an involutive-algebra or a \(*\)-algebra.</p> <ul> <li>A subset is said to be self-adjoint if \(a\in S \implies a^*\in S\).</li> <li>An element \(a\in \mathcal{A}\) is <em>normal</em> if \(aa^* = a^* a\).</li> <li>\(p \in \mathcal{A}\) is a <em>projection</em> if \(p = p^* = p^2\).</li> <li>\(u \in \mathcal{A}\) is <em>unitary</em> if \(uu^* = u^*u = 1\).</li> </ul> <p>A <em>Banach algebra</em> is a \(*\)-algebra with a complete, submultiplicative norm which obeys \(||a|| = ||a^*||\). A \(C^*\)-algebra is a Banach \(*\)-algebra obeying \begin{equation} ||a^*a|| = ||a||^2. \end{equation}</p>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An algebra is a vector space with more to do with. Formally, if \(V\) is a vector space over the field \(\mathbb{F}\), then an algebra \(\mathcal{A}\) over \(\mathbb{F}\) is the vector space together with a bilinear multiplication operation defined on it, \(\mathcal{A} = (F,\cdot)\) with \(\cdot: V\times V \to V\), \((a,b) \mapsto a\cdot b \equiv ab\) for \(a,b\in V\). The multiplication is usually associative, \(a(bc) = (ab)c\), hence usally the algebras are associative algebras.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactions and Integrability</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/intint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactions and Integrability"/><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/intint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/intint/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="interactions-and-integrability">Interactions and integrability</h2> <p>In this brief note we outline two key concepts in quantum many-body (QMB) theory, which are immensly helpful both theoretically and numerically.</p> <h3 id="non-interacting-systems">Non-interacting systems</h3> <p>These are the simplest to study, as we see now. Simply stated, a QMB system is <em>non-interacting</em> if it can be diagonalized exactly over single particle terms. The Hamiltonian of a non-interacting, also called <em>free</em> (or sometimes <em>Gaussian</em> if we borrow a bit of field theory jargon) and admits some flavor of the following decomposition,</p> <p>\begin{equation} H = \sum_k \varepsilon_k a_k^\dagger a_k \end{equation}</p> <p>here \(k\) labels the different particles, which do not <em>interact</em> with each other. Here \(\{a_k,a_k^\dagger\}_k\) are creation and annhilation operators for each particle \(k\), which could be bosonic or fermionic. Nonetheless, the key is for \(N\) particle, this object is a matrix of linear size \(O(N)\), instead of exponential, and in-fact the eigenstates are super simple. For any \(\mathcal{K} \subseteq \{1,2,\dots,N\}\),</p> <p>\begin{equation} H \left[\prod_{k \in \mathcal{K}} a_k^\dagger |0\rangle\right] = \left(\sum_{k\in \mathcal{K}} \varepsilon_k\right) \left[\prod_{k \in \mathcal{K}} a_k^\dagger |0\rangle\right] \end{equation}</p> <h3 id="interacting-systems">Interacting systems</h3> <p>Well, the particles <em>interact</em>. For instance, Hamiltonians containing terms like \(n_i n_j\) with \(n_k := a_k^\dagger a_k\) cannot be brought to the form above. This induces an exponentially complex Hilbert space, with no analytical solutions in general except for special cases. So the Hamiltonian cannot be written as a sum of decoupled single-particle terms. These effects include scattering and collective phenomenon, and are really the most interesting to study.</p> <h3 id="integrable-systems">Integrable systems</h3> <p>A QMB system is said to be <em>integrable</em> if it possesses an extensive set of conserved quantities (operators) \(\{Q_i\}_i\), which are</p> <ul> <li>mutually commuting, \([Q_i,Q_j] = 0\)</li> <li>commute with the Hamiltonian \([Q_i,H] = 0\) (are <em>conserved</em>)</li> </ul> <p>The Hamiltonian is trivially a conserved quantity, always. These systems are <em>solvable</em> as well, because each eigenstate of the Hamiltonian can be uniquely specified as per it’s charge under the conserved quantitites \(Q_i\), \(\psi \leftrightarrow (q_1,q_2,\dots)\). Such equations can be solved with polynomial complexity as well, as opposed to exponential. Integrable systems exhibit regular, predictable behavior due to their conserved quantities. Integrable systems avoid thermalization owing to the extensive set of conserved quantities.</p> <h3 id="non-integrable">Non-integrable</h3> <p>No such extensive set of conserved quantities. One corner here is that the only conserved quantity is energy, i.e., the Hamiltonian. In random circuits, even that is taken away, making them interesting unstructured objects to study.</p> <p>Then, one could take a Cartesian product, and have three (non-interacting non-integrable does not really exist) classes,</p> <ol> <li><em>Non-interacting, integrable</em>. Free systems are integrable by definition, the conserved quantities are just the particle numbers.</li> <li><em>Interacting, integrable</em>. Systems with interactions yet stil solvable through the extensive conserved quantities, can have stable quasiparticles, do not thermalize conventionally, perhaps solvable through Bethe ansatz methods.</li> <li><em>Interacting, non-integrable</em>. The most interesting, and “generic” case, no exact solutions, typically “chaotic” and thermalizing. The <em>real world</em>.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="many-body"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Interactions and integrability]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Entanglement Negativity</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/negativity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Entanglement Negativity"/><published>2025-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/negativity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/negativity/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="setting">Setting</h2> <p>We are interested in quantum systems defined on a system \(S = A \cup B\), and quantifying the entanglement between the A and B subsystems. Let \(\mathcal{H}_X\) denote the Hilbert space of register \(X\), so \(\mathcal{H}_S = \mathcal{H}_A \otimes \mathcal{H}_B\). A quantum state on \(X\) is a unit-trace positive operator \(\rho\in \mathcal{D}(\mathcal{H}_X)\). A state is pure iff it is rank-one. Owing to the annoyance caused by writing kets and bras without the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">physics</code> package, I will just write \(\psi\) to denote the density matrix of a pure state.</p> <p>Let us first set the ground and talk about the simpler case. For <em>pure</em> states, the notion of entanglement is very well defined and well captured by von-Neumann entropy. Specifically, if I define the reduced state of A as \(\rho_A = tr_B(\psi)\), then the entropy \(S(\rho_A) = -tr(\rho_A \log{\rho_A})\) captures the amount of entanglement in the bipartition \(A \cup B\). This is often called the entropy of entanglement. Operationally, in the limit of a large number of copies of the state, this quantity quantifies</p> <ul> <li><em>dilution</em> the asymptotic number of Bell pairs between A and B needed (per copy) to prepare the state via local operations and classical communications (LOCC)</li> <li><em>distillation</em> the asymptotic number of Bell pairs that can be created (per copy) from the state via LOCC</li> </ul> <p>Hence, the entropy of entanglement is a fundamental quantity for pure states, and does a good job at characterizing the entanglement.</p> <h2 id="mixed-states">Mixed States</h2> <p>It is trivial to see that the von-Neumann entropy, or any Renyi entropy for that matter, is not a good object to characterize mixed-state entanglement. A counter example is given by the fully mixed state, exhibiting no correlations of any kind yet scoring high on entropies. To build up the story for mixed state, we must first understand what’s <em>not</em> entangled. Well, a pure state is not entangled if it can be written as a product across that bipartition. It turns out a mixed state is not entangled if it can be written in the following form,</p> <p>\begin{equation} \rho_{AB} = \sum_i p_i \rho_A^i \otimes \rho_B^i \end{equation}</p> <p>and any state of the form above is said to be <em>separable</em> (with respect to that bipartition). The reason any such object is not entangled (again, across that bipartition!) is because such a state can always be prepared by LOCC on that bipartition, and hence displays classical correlations. One cannot create entanglement via LOCC. Specifically, there <em>could be</em> correlations in the state, but they are classical and the extent of those correlations is quantified by the Shannon entropy of the distribution \(p\).</p> <h2 id="ppt-test">PPT Test</h2> <p>Well then, I give you the state \(\rho_{AB}\), how do you tell me if it is entangled? One way, and perhaps the most prominent way, to answer this question was given in [1] by Peres. Specifically, they outline the following: <strong>if a state is separable, it’s partial transpose must be positive</strong>. Let us unpack this. What is the transpose? Well, it’s a map \(A \mapsto A^{T}\) such that \([A^{T}]_{ij} := [A]_{ji}\). A <em>partial</em> transpose is when we transpose only the \(A(B)\) subsystem, we denote this as \(\rho^{T_A}\).</p> <p>The proof is trivial, note that if \(\sigma\) is a valid density matrix, then so is \(\sigma^T\). Hence, upon partial transposing a separable state, we get another valid density matrix, which must be positive. Hence, any separable state has a positive partial tranpose—we say that it <em>passes</em> the PPT test.</p> <p>If a state does not pass PPT, we denote it to be NPT. Then, we can say that a state which is NPT must be entangled. However, the chain of impliciations must be paid attention to. There <em>do exist</em> entangled states which are PPT. Thus, if I give you a state and it passes PPT, a priori we cannot say if it is entangled or not. However, if it <em>violates</em> PPT and is thus NPT, then we say that it is entangled.</p> <p>\begin{equation} \text{Separable} \implies \text{PPT} \end{equation}</p> <p>\begin{equation} \text{NPT} \implies \text{Entangled} \end{equation}</p> <p>It is good to note a stronger statements proven for \(2 \otimes 2\) and \(2 \otimes 3\). In [2], the \(\text{Horodecki}^{\otimes 3}\) proved that for these dimensions, PPT and separability are equivalent.</p> <p>\begin{equation} (2 \otimes 2) \text{ and } (2 \otimes 3) : \text{PPT} \Leftrightarrow \text{Separable} \end{equation}</p> <h2 id="negativity">Negativity</h2> <p>We then perform the following task. Take the state \(\rho_{AB}\), partial transpose it \(\rho_{AB}^{T_A}\), and find it’s spectrum \(\Lambda(\rho_{AB}^{T_A}) = \{\lambda_i\}_i\). Then, define,</p> <p>\begin{equation} \mathcal{N}(\rho_{AB}) := \sum_{\lambda_i : \lambda_i &lt; 0} |\lambda_i| \end{equation}</p> <p>If this quantity is positive, we have entanglement. This is called <em>negativity</em>. That is \(\mathcal{N}(\rho_{AB}) = 0\) for separable states. A nicer way to write this down is,</p> <p>\begin{equation} \mathcal{N}(\rho_{AB}) := \frac{||\rho_{AB}^{T_A}||_1 - 1}{2} \end{equation}</p> <p>where \(\|O\|_1 := tr\sqrt{O^{\dagger}O}\) is the trace norm. Another quantity born out of this discussion is the <em>logarithmic negativity</em>,</p> <p>\begin{equation} E_N(\rho_{AB}) := \log_2||\rho_{AB}^{T_A}||<em>1 \equiv \log_2(2\mathcal{N}(\rho</em>{AB}) + 1) \end{equation}</p> <p>These quantities first showed up in [4], and are now commonly used in analyzing mixed state entanglement.</p> <h2 id="distillable-entanglement">Distillable entanglement</h2> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p>[1] Peres, Asher. “Separability criterion for density matrices.” Physical Review Letters 77.8 (1996): 1413.</p> <p>[2] Horodecki, Michal, Pawel Horodecki, and Ryszard Horodecki. “On the necessary and sufficient conditions for separability of mixed quantum states.” Phys. Lett. A 223.1 (1996).</p> <p>[3] Horodecki, Michał, Paweł Horodecki, and Ryszard Horodecki. “Mixed-state entanglement and distillation: Is there a “bound” entanglement in nature?.” Physical Review Letters 80.24 (1998): 5239.</p> <p>[4] Vidal, Guifré, and Reinhard F. Werner. “Computable measure of entanglement.” Physical Review A 65.3 (2002): 032314.</p>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="qi"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Setting]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Floquet things</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/floquet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Floquet things"/><published>2025-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/floquet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/floquet/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="periodically-driven-quantum-systems">Periodically Driven Quantum Systems</h2> <p>The Hamiltonian is periodic in time with some period \(T\), viz.,</p> <p>\begin{equation} H(t + T) = H(t) \end{equation}</p> <p>Such systems can be thought of as <em>driven</em>, where energy is periodically pumped in and out of the system. That is, energy is conserved modulo single photon exchanges, with \(\omega = 2\pi/T\),</p> <p>\begin{equation} h/T = hf = \hbar\omega \end{equation}</p> <p>The key idea underlying Floquet theory is to separate the long (<strong>stroboscopic</strong>) and short time scales, for \(n\) driving periods we have,</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(t + nT) = U(t)[U(T)]^n \end{equation}</p> <p>Here, the <em>Floquet operator</em> is defined as,</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(T) := \mathcal{T} \exp{-\iota\int_{t=0}^T H(t)dt} \end{equation}</p> <p>where \(\mathcal{T}\) denotes time ordering in the exponential. We define the <em>Floquet Hamiltonian</em> \(H_F\) as,</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(T) =: e^{-\iota H_F T} \end{equation}</p> <p>Thus we have a separation into <em>short scale</em> (through \(V(t)\)) and <em>long scale</em> (through \(H_F\)) dynamics as,</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(t) \sim V(t) \cdot \exp{(-\iota H_F t)} <br/> \end{equation}</p> <p>where \(V(t) = V(t+T)\). The Floquet operator is unitary and admits eigenvalues on the unit circle \(\Lambda(U(T)) \subset \mathcal{U}(1)\),</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(T)|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = \lambda_{\alpha}|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle \end{equation}</p> <p>with \(\lambda_{\alpha}\in\mathcal{U}(1)\). If the spectrum is gapped, we identify a <em>cut</em> \(\varepsilon\) such that \(e^{-\iota \varepsilon} \not\in \Lambda(U(T))\). Then we have,</p> <p>\begin{equation} H_F := \frac{\iota}{T}\log_{-\varepsilon}U(T) \end{equation}</p> <p>also has the same eigenstates,</p> <p>\begin{equation} H_F|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = \epsilon_{\alpha} |\phi_{\alpha}\rangle \end{equation}</p> <p>but the <em>quasienergies</em> \(\epsilon_{\alpha}\) are only defined in</p> <p>\begin{equation} \epsilon_{\alpha} \in [-\pi/T,\pi/T] \end{equation}</p> <p>Time periodic Floquet modes are defined as the action of the microscopic operator on the eigenstates,</p> <p>\begin{equation} |u_{\alpha}(t)\rangle := V(t)|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = |u_{\alpha}(t+T)\rangle \end{equation}</p> <p>we note that</p> <p>\begin{equation} U(t)|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = V(t)e^{-\iota H_Ft}|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = e^{-\iota \epsilon_{\alpha}t}V(t)|\phi_{\alpha}\rangle = e^{-\iota \epsilon_{\alpha}t}|u_{\alpha}(t)\rangle \end{equation}</p> <p>Thus, \begin{equation} U(t,t’) = \sum_{\alpha} e^{−\iota (t-t’)\epsilon_{\alpha}} |u_{\alpha}(t)\rangle \langle u_{\alpha}(t’)| \end{equation}</p> <p>The \(u_{\alpha}(t)\) describe the micro motion, and are the same as the \(\phi_{\alpha}\) at every stroboscopic time point.</p>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="many-body"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Periodically Driven Quantum Systems]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parity Superselection</title><link href="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parity Superselection"/><published>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://siddhantmidha.com/blog/2025/fermions/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="fermions">Fermions</h2> <p>In the language of second quantization, we describe fermions in terms of the annhilation \(c\) and creation operators \(c^\dagger\). Consider a system of \(N\) fermionic modes. Then, the anti-commutation relations are as follows:</p> \[\{ c_i,c_j^\dagger \} = \delta_{ij} , \{ c_i^\dagger,c_j^\dagger \} = 0, \{ c_i,c_j \} = 0\] <p>The corresponding Majorana operators are defined as,</p> \[\gamma_i := (a_i + a_i^\dagger) , \bar{\gamma}_i := -\iota (a_i - a_i^\dagger)\] <p>These objects are Hermitian, \(\gamma = \gamma^\dagger\) and \(\bar{\gamma} = \bar{\gamma}^\dagger\), and they satisfy the following anti-commutation relations,</p> \[\{ \gamma_i,\gamma_j \} = 2\delta_{ij}\] <p>Another interesting object to define in terms of the Majorana operators are <em>edge</em> and <em>vertex</em> operators [1]. For each \(i,j \in [N]\),</p> \[E_{ij} := -\iota \gamma_i\gamma_j, V_j:= -\iota \gamma_j \bar{\gamma}_j\] <p>These objects are Hermitian, traceless, and self-inverse. They obey a nice graph-theoretic notion of (anti-)commutativity. That is, if a vertex is shared among these objects, they anticommute. If they are disjoint, they commute.</p> \[\{ E_{jk},V_j \} = 0, \{ E_{ij},E_{jk} \} = 0\] <p>and if \((i,j,k,l)\) are all distinct, then</p> \[[V_i,V_j] = 0, [E_{ij},V_k] = 0, [E_{ij},E_{kl}] = 0.\] <h2 id="parity-superselection-rule">Parity (superselection rule)</h2> <p>The number operator for mode \(i\) is defined as \(n_i = c_i^\dagger c_i\), and the total number operator is \(n = \sum_i n_i\). With this, we define the parity operator as follows,</p> \[\mathcal{P} := (-1)^n.\] <p>We say that a state is in a definite parity state if it is an eigenstate of the parity operator. Note that \(\mathcal{P}\) only has \(\pm 1\) eigenvalues. The <em>parity superselection rule</em> tells us the following: nature does not allow physical states to be in coherent superposition of states with different parity. Phrased another way, every physical state has to be in a definite parity sector. Furthermore, <em>physical</em> operations then must respect parity: they must commute with the parity operator. That is why one never sees a term like \(c + c^\dagger\) in a fermionic Hamiltonian, or why one can never measure such an operator. To obtain insight into this “rule,” let us consider the following <em>gedankenexperimente</em> [2,3]. Consider two parties, Alice and Bob. They share the following (non-normalized) state</p> \[|\psi\rangle = (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle\] <p>where \(\Omega\) is the vacuum. We see that this state is a superposition of different parities. Now suppose Alice wants to send one bit of classical information to Bob, with \(b \in \{ 0,1 \}\). Define</p> \[U_0 := I ,U_1 := \iota(c_A^\dagger - c_A)\] <p>Corresponding to the value of the bit \(b\), Alice applies the unitary \(U_b\), and Bob measures the operator \(\mathcal{O}=(1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger)\). Then, we claim that this allows deterministic superluminal communication of the bit \(b\). Note that this is not a teleportation like claim, where we actually have to send some information to tell Bob the correct basis to measure in. The <em>weird</em> thing about this is that, the basis is determined already. We now see that this is true just because of the anticommutation relations, thereby showing (empirically, atleast) parity superselection. The result after applying the unitary is,</p> \[|\psi_0\rangle = (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle\] \[|\psi_1\rangle = (1-c_B^\dagger)c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle\] \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_0\rangle= (1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger) (1 + c_B^\dagger) |\Omega\rangle =2(|\Omega\rangle + c_B^\dagger|\Omega\rangle) = 2|\psi_0\rangle\] \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_1\rangle = (1 + c_B + c_B^\dagger)(1-c_B^\dagger)c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle = c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle - c_B^\dagger c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle - c_A^\dagger|\Omega\rangle + c_B^\dagger c_A^\dagger |\Omega\rangle = 0\] <p>Thus, both of these states are eigenstates of the operator \(\mathcal{O}\), viz.</p> \[\mathcal{O}|\psi_b\rangle = E_b|\psi_b\rangle\] <p>and measuring this observable thus perfectly distinguishes them, and Alice manages to transmit the bit perfectly at superluminal speed. We reach a contradiction.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol> <li>Derby, Charles, et al. “Compact fermion to qubit mappings.” Physical Review B 104.3 (2021): 035118.</li> <li>Szalay, Szilárd, et al. “Fermionic systems for quantum information people.” Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 54.39 (2021): 393001.</li> <li>Vidal, Nicetu Tibau, et al. “Quantum operations in an information theory for fermions.” Physical Review A 104.3 (2021): 032411.</li> <li>Friis, Nicolai, Antony R. Lee, and David Edward Bruschi. “Fermionic-mode entanglement in quantum information.” Physical Review A—Atomic, Molecular, and Optical Physics 87.2 (2013): 022338.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Siddhant</name></author><category term="many-body"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fermions In the language of second quantization, we describe fermions in terms of the annhilation \(c\) and creation operators \(c^\dagger\). Consider a system of \(N\) fermionic modes. Then, the anti-commutation relations are as follows:]]></summary></entry></feed>